Guide to the Judi Chapman Papers 1963-1999
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
- Indian organizations, 1972-1999; Series III; 3.9 linear feet
  - Grants and Head Start reviews, 1991-1999; Subseries 3; 1.9 linear feet
    - Department of Education Vocational Education, 1995 (Box 29)
      Information about the technical review process for the Indian Vocational Education Program
    - Dull Knife / Northern Cheyenne, 1991 (Box 29)
      regarding IRS assessment issued to Dull Knife Memorial College for period of non payment of FICA tax and resolution. Draft Letters, memorandum and supporting evidence
    - Northern Cheyenne Head Start, undated (Box 30)
      consulting project to bring Northern Cheyenne Headstart Disabilities Component info compliance; correspondence; recommendations; Headstart program performance standards definition
    - American Indians, Alaska Natives, and Native Hawaiians Commission, undated (Box 30)
      miscellaneous papers, news clippings
    - American Indian Business Leader, undated (Box 30)
    - American Business Leader grant application, undated (Box 30)
    - Indian and Active American Employment and Training Coalition, undated (Box 30)
    - National commission on American Indians, Alaska Natives, and Native Hawaiians., undated (Box 31)
      Housing correspondence, memorandums
    - Report and labor statistics, 1992 (Box 31)
- City of Missoula and Missoula County, 1992-1997; Series IV; 0.1 linear feet
  This series contains flyers, reports, and correspondence related to Chapman’s work with the City of Missoula and Missoula. Specifically, materials in this series relate to Chapman’s work to address health, environmental, and Native American issues.
  - Advisory Council, 1995 (Box-folder 12/5)
  - Benchmarks, 1996 (Box-folder 12/6)
  - Crime, 1994 (Box-folder 12/7)
  - Food handling, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 12/8)
  - Growth, 1997 (Box-folder 12/9)
  - Healthy Profile Task Force, 1994 (Box-folder 12/10)
  - Immunization, undated (Box-folder 12/11)
  - Infectious diseases, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 12/12)
  - Maternal and child health, undated (Box-folder 12/13)
  - Medicaid, undated (Box-folder 12/14)
  - Medical negligence, 1995 (Box-folder 12/15)
  - Missoula County Health Department Mission Statement, 1996 (Box-folder 12/16)
  - Nursing home reform, 1992 (Box-folder 12/17)
- Democratic Party, 1982-1997; Series V; 2.2 linear feet
  This series contains materials related to Chapman’s work as a delegate to the 1996 Democratic National Convention and the get out the vote effort lead by the Montana Alliance for Progressive Policy. This series consists primarily of subject files related specific political issues and voter registration.
  - Max Baucus correspondence, 1991 (Box-folder 13/1)
  - Canvassing – George McGovern and Sargent Schriver, 1972 (Box-folder 13/2)
  - Jimmy Carter – Indians, 1978-1988 (Box-folder 13/3)
  - Chicago – Democratic National Convention, 1996 (Box-folder 13/4)
  - Frank Church, 1976 (Box-folder 13/5)
  - Bill Clinton - general, 1992-1996 (Box-folder 13/6-7)
    1995 State of the Union notes, acceptance speech from the 1992 Democratic National Convention, talking points, position papers
  - Bill Clinton – Billings meeting, 1995 (Box-folder 13/8)
  - Bill Clinton Discovers the Indian Vote, 1992 (Box-folder 13/9)
  - Bill Clinton – Gaming, undated (Box-folder 13/10)
  - Bill Clinton 1993 inauguration, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 13/11)
  - Bill Clinton 1997 inauguration (Box-folder 13/12)
  - Bill Clinton transition, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 14/1)
    1993 transition to Clinton Administration by tribal organizations, position papers
  - Coordinated Campaign, 1995 (Box-folder 14/2)
    Montana Democratic Party campaign plans
  - Coordinated Campaign for Indian voters, 1996 (Box-folder 14/3)
  - Council of Energy Resource Tribes (CERT) political empowerment, 1994 (Box-folder 14/4)
  - Crow – 1992 election (Box-folder 14/5)
  - Ada Deer – Assistant Secretary for Indian Affairs, 1993 (Box-folder 14/6)
  - Delegates, 1988 (Box-folder 14/7)
    Native American delegates to 1988 Democratic National Convention
  - Democratic National Committee, 1989-1996 (Box-folder 14/8)
  - Democratic National Convention, 1992 (Box-folder 14/9)
  - Democratic National Convention – Indian issues, 1992 (Box-folder 14/10)
  - Democratic National platform, 1976-1992 (Box-folder 14/11)
  - Democratic Party, 1980-1996 (Box-folder 14/12)
  - Democratic Party Indian platform, 1992 (Box-folder 14/13)
  - Democratic Party Montana, 1983-1994 (Box-folder 15/1)
  - Democratic Party Montana - Indian platform, 1994 (Box-folder 15/2)
  - Democratic Party Montana platform, 1980-1996 (Box-folder 15/3-4)
  - Discover the Indian Vote (DIV) – Montana Handout, 1992 (Box-folder 15/5)
  - Bob Dole, 1996 (Box-folder 15/6)
  - Dorgan – news clipping (Box-folder 15/7)
  - Michael Dukakis – Indians, 1988 (Box-folder 15/8)
  - Larry Echohawk – 1990 campaign information and news clippings, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 15/9)
  - Election data - Montana, 1988 (Box-folder 15/10)
  - Election judges – Missoula, 1994 (Box-folder 15/11)
  - Elections, 1990 (Box-folder 15/12)
  - Emily’s List, 1989 (Box-folder 15/13)
  - Forms – Montana Alliance for Progressive Policy, 1992 (Box-folder 15/14)
  - Flathead – Flathead Reservation voter registration, 1992 (Box-folder 15/15)
  - Fort Peck – voter registration, 1992 (Box-folder 15/16)
  - Fort Belknap – voter registration, 1992 (Box-folder 15/17)
  - Fund Raising – Democratic National Convention, Spokane Tribe, 1996 (Box-folder 15/18)
  - Barry Goldwater, 1983 (Box-folder 15/19)
  - Jesse Jackson, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 15/20)
  - Emery Keoke, 1974-1987 (Box-folder 16/1)
  - Tom Katus, 1977-1990 (Box-folder 16/2)
  - Listening Conference – tribal leaders, 1994 (Box-folder 16/3)
  - Ron Marlenee – information, newsletters, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 16/4)
  - George McGovern – crisis letter, 1974 (Box-folder 16/5)
  - Media – use of media, circa 1994 (Box-folder 16/6)
  - Montana Delegation Selection Convention, 1996 (Box-folder 16/7)
  - National Indian Deomcrats, 1984-1991 (Box-folder 16/8)
  - Native Action's Proposal – Montana Indian voter Education Project, 1994 (Box-folder 16/9)
  - Native Americans for Bill Clinton and Al Gore, 1992 (Box-folder 16/10)
  - Indian political empowerment, 1992 (Box-folder 16/11)
  - Ronald Reagan – Indians, 1983-1988 (Box-folder 16/12)
  - Redistricting – reapportionment, 1994 (Box-folder 16/13)
  - Republicans – notes and platforms, 1980-1996 (Box-folder 16/14)
  - Sovereignty, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 16/15)
  - Standing Rock – news clippings, memos, circa 1988 (Box-folder 16/16)
  - Success – record of legislative successes, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 17/1)
  - Supreme Court decision, 1983 (Box-folder 17/2)
  - Sweet Grass Hills, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 17/3)
    Religious and cultural significance, Bureau of Land Management mining proposals
  - Taxes - tribal taxation of non Indians, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 17/4)
  - Tax Credits – Indian Employment opportunity, 1992 (Box-folder 17/5)
  - Tax - non-Indians, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 17/6)
  - Title XX – Social Services Block Grant, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 17/7)
  - Treaties – news clippings, memos, reports, Hellgate Treaty, 1987 (Box-folder 17/8)
  - Trust – policy paper, 1979-1990 (Box-folder 17/9)
  - Trust fund management, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 17/10)
  - Udall – news clipping, undated (Box-folder 17/11)
  - Vocational rehabilitation, 1987 (Box-folder 17/12)
    grants 1987, list of vocational rehabilitation grant readers, Rehabilitation Act of 1973, amendments 1984, memos, white papers, study of Special Problems and Needs of American Indians with handicaps on and off the Reservations 1987
  - Water Rights, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 17/13)
    Criteria and Procedures – Federal register notice, personal notes, letters, position papers, report – western water, Federal and Indian rights
  - James Watt - letter to Editor, Washington Post, September 1982 (Box-folder 17/14)
  - Welfare, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 17/15)
    Welfare reform and Indian country position papers, 1995, news articles, personal notes, tribes plans
  - Women - Native American women counselors, 1993 (Box-folder 17/16)
  - Wounded Knee – news clippings, historical file, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 18/1)
  - Yakima Nation, 1990 (Box-folder 18/2)
    Impact Aid, School Construction for Indian People, Yakima County right to tax lands owned by individual tribal members and the tribes
  - Year of the American Indian, 1992 (Box-folder 18/3)
    Resolution to proclaim year of American Indian
  - Youth, 1991 (Box-folder 18/4)
- Subject files, 1963-1999; Series VI; 2.8 linear feet
  This series consists of clippings and correspondence organized according to subject. It is divided into two subseries: General subject files and Native American subject files.
  - General subject files, 1963-1999; Subseries 1; 1.0 linear feet
    This subseries consists of files reflecting Chapman’s political work, both during and after her years as an assistant to Pat Williams. Files consisting entirely of unannotated clippings or publications were removed from this subseries.
    - Assertiveness workshop, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 18/5-6)
      correspondence, training materials, news clippings, personal notes, Montana Assertive Collective for Women
    - American Civil Liberties Union, 1992 (Box-folder 18/7)
      letter regarding Reapportionment Commission’s decision to fragment Blackfeet and Flathead tribes
    - Dave Barry – clippings, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 18/8)
    - Career education – career development curriculum, 1972 (Box-folder 18/9)
    - Child care, 1990 (Box-folder 18/10)
      Child Care and Development Black Grant, 1990; childcare provisions in budget reconciliation; news clippings
    - Child labor, 1992 (Box-folder 18/11)
    - Church and state, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 18/12)
    - Counseling, circa 1975, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 18/13)
    - Defense and education, 1982 (Box-folder 18/14)
    - Discussion materials, 1972 (Box-folder 18/15)
    - Energy speech, undated (Box-folder 18/16)
    - Environment, undated (Box-folder 18/17)
    - FMLA - Family Medical Leave Act, 1993 (Box-folder 19/1)
    - Federal role in education, 1981 (Box-folder 19/2)
      NEA policy paper, Department of Education papers
    - Human Rights, 1993-1996 (Box-folder 19/3)
    - Integrated studies, undated (Box-folder 19/4)
      interview with Jack Barden, University of North Dakota
    - Japan, 1970-1996 (Box-folder 19/5)
    - Japan Club, 1994-1997 (Box-folder 19/6)
    - Japan - Mansfield Center, 1983-1991 (Box-folder 19/7)
    - Martin Luther King, 1986-1991 (Box-folder 19/8)
    - Managed care – personal notes, undated (Box-folder 19/9)
    - National Endowment for the Arts – letters to the editor, 1993 (Box-folder 19/10)
    - Parliamentary procedures, undated (Box-folder 19/11)
    - Peace, 1963-1996 (Box-folder 19/12)
    - Peace (continued), 1963-1997 (Box-folder 20/1-2)
    - Michael Saba, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 20/3)
    - James Watt on Indian issues, 1983, January 19, 1983 (Box 26)
      Cassette tape. Topic very similar to a United Press Interational (UPI) article published on the same date by the New York Times.
    - James Watt on Indian issues, 1983 (use copy), January 19, 1983 (Box 26)
    - Woodstock, 1994 (Box-folder 20/4)
  - Native American subject files, 1982-1995; Subseries 2; 1.8 linear feet
    - Administration for Native Americans - funds for 1997, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 20/5)
    - Administration for Native Americans - training and technical assistance, 1996 (Box-folder 20/6)
      Title on folder: ANA T and TA
    - Bureau of Indian Affairs reorganization, 1992 – 1994 (Box-folder 20/7)
    - Bureau of Indian Affairs school review, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 21/1-2)
    - CDBG (Community Development Block Grants), 1983 (Box-folder 21/3)
    - CAP - Congressional Advocacy Planners – Drafting Federal Law, 1994 (Box-folder 21/4)
    - Contacts - Missoula Indian Center, 1990-1997 (Box-folder 21/5)
    - Contacts - Tribal leaders list, 1995 (Box-folder 21/6)
    - Contacts - ATNI (Affiliated Tribes of Northwest Indians), 1996 (Box-folder 21/7)
    - Council of Energy Resource Tribes, 1994 (Box-folder 21/8)
    - Department of Commerce – telecommunications, 1995 (Box-folder 21/9)
    - Lucille Echohawk – Council of Energy Resource Tribes managers, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 22/1)
    - Environmental Protection Agency conference, 1996 (Box-folder 22/2)
    - First nations – correspondence, 1994 (Box-folder 22/3)
    - Housing and Urban Development drug elimination program, 1997 (Box-folder 22/4)
    - Housing – Indian housing issues, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 22/5)
    - Indian Peoples Action, 1997 (Box-folder 22/6)
    - Indians – general, 1975-1996 (Box-folder 22/7)
    - Iroquois, undated (Box-folder 22/8)
    - JTPA (Job Training Partnership Act), 1995-1996 (Box-folder 22/9)
    - Jurisdiction – state and Indian jurisdictions, 1978-1990 (Box-folder 22/10)
    - Justice – notes regarding Tribal Justice Act, 1998 (Box-folder 22/11)
    - Law – Supreme Court and Indian law, circa 1991 (Box-folder 22/12)
    - Law Enforcement, 1993 (Box-folder 23/1)
      Bureau of Indian Affairs brutality news clippings, notes
    - Library – tribal colleges and serving Native Americans, undated (Box-folder 23/2)
    - Little Bighorn – legislation for memorial, 1990 (Box-folder 23/3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1986-1992 (Box-folder 23/4)
    - Miskito Indians of Nicaragua – letter for Pat Williams to President Carter, 1989 (Box-folder 23/5)
    - Montana - Indians, 1983-1994 (Box-folder 23/6)
    - Montana trips – Pat Williams, 1979-1989 (Box-folder 23/7)
    - National Commission of Native Governments, 1992 (Box-folder 23/8)
      A Bill recognizing native governments, edited by Judi Chapman
    - National Congress of American Indians, 1991-1996 (Box-folder 23/9)
    - National Indian Policy Center, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 23/10)
      Draft Bill establishing National Indian Policy Center and supporting organizational documents 1991
    - National Museum of American Indians, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 23/11)
    - Native America Grave Protection and Repatriation Act, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 23/12)
    - North American Free Trade Agreement, 1993 (Box-folder 23/13)
    - Nuclear Waste, 1993 (Box-folder 23/14)
    - Oil theft, 1989 (Box-folder 23/15)
    - Oliphant versus Suquamish tribe, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 23/16)
    - Pesticides, 1996 (Box-folder 23/17)
      Title VI and Indian Tribes and authority regarding regulation of pesticides
    - Phelps – Stokes Fund, 1985 (Box-folder 23/18)
    - Policy, 1984-1992 (Box-folder 24/1)
    - Preference – Employment of Native Americans, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 24/2)
    - Racism – Indians, 1982-1990 (Box-folder 24/3)
    - Racism - Indian response to racism, 1990 (Box-folder 24/4)
    - Religion – Indian religious freedom and environment education, 1979-1993 (Box-folder 24/5)
    - Rocky Boy, 1987-1997 (Box-folder 24/6)
    - Safety of dams, 1990 (Box-folder 24/7)
    - Salish – Kootenai Tribes, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 24/8)
    - Self-determination, 1987-1993 (Box-folder 24/9-10)
    - Self–governance, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 25/1)
    - Self governance / 638 comparison, 1993 (Box-folder 25/2)
    - Self governance - 638 regulations, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 25/3)
- Mountain-Plains Education and Economic Development Program, 1972-1973; Series VII; 0.8 linear feet
  This series contains materials related to Chapman’s work as Senior Instructor of Educational and Social Services with the Mountain-Plains Education and Economic Development Program, based on Glasgow Air Force Base in Glasgow, Montana. The program was based on a model of “family oriented career education,” which was intended to improve vocational education for disadvantaged families by providing educational, financial, and social support through an on-site training program. Materials in this series include training and educational materials used in the program, much of which Chapman authored, correspondence, and notes.
  - Mountain-Plains Education and Economic Development Program, 1972-1973 (Box 25-26)